Guide to the Ralph Kaiser Papers on the Allegheny Home Rule Charter, 1997-1999 AIS.2003.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ralph Kaiser Papers on the Allegheny County Home Rule Charter
1997-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kaiser, Ralph E.
AIS.2003.11
1.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Ralph Kaiser was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives (Democrat) from the City of Pittsburgh, Pa., in 1989 and served until 2002. During his time in the House, he held a position as a member of the Allegheny County Charter Draft Committee, the main organization behind the push for the Allegheny Home Rule Charter. This collection contains newspaper clippings of articles, meeting minutes, agendas, correspondence, and ephemera related to the home rule charter.
History
In accordance with The Home Rule Charter and Optional Plans Law (Act 62 of 1972), which mandates the study of a county's existing government structure before changes can be submitted, Allegheny County was given permission to draft its own charter after the passage of the Second Class County Charter Law (Act 12 of 1997). The draft went through several revisions, based on Allegheny County Charter Draft Committee member and public feedback. The vote to ratify the home rule charter took place on May 19, 1998, during the Pennsylvania Primary elections. The charter eliminated the three county commissioner governing system and replaced it with elected officials: a county council and chief executive. The 15 member county council was elected in November 1999 and took office in January 2000.
Scope and Content Notes
The Ralph Kaiser Papers on the Allegheny County Home Rule Charter documents the Allegheny County Drafting Committee work toward a home rule charter for Allegheny County. The collection consists of the Allegheny Home Rule Charter drafts with corresponding notes, edits, and criticisms of the drafts. The bulk of the collection comes from newspaper clippings that Representative Kaiser collected from 1997 to 1999, providing a concise documentation of public opinion of the campaign from its inception to the drafts passage and the Allegheny County redistricting efforts that followed as a result of the passage of the charter. This part of the collection includes articles and op-ed pieces on the home rule charter, election results, committee selection, re-districting efforts after the passage of the charter and demographic profiles on the newly created districts. Transcripts and list of presenters at public hearings for the charter, personal correspondence concerning the charter, as well as a small collection of campaign items from both sides of the issue, are included in the collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Ralph Kaiser Papers on the Allegheny Home Rule Charter, 1997-1999, AIS. 2003.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ralph Kaiser in November 2003.
Correspondence; Politics; Clippings (Information artifacts); County government -- Law and legislation -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; County charters -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Charters; Legislators -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Allegheny County (Pa.). Charter Drafting Committee; Kaiser, Ralph E.; Allegheny County (Pa.). Government Study Commission
- Allegheny County Charter Drafting Committee Business, October-December 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Allegheny County Charter Drafting Committee Business, December 1997-June 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Allegheny County Drafting Committee Agenda and Minutes, July 1997-February 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Allegheny County Home Rule Charter Drafts, September 1997-October 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Allegheny County Home Rule Charter Drafts, November 1997-December 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Allegheny County Home Rule Charter Drafts, January 1998-May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Allegheny County Home Rule Charter Info, May 1997-November 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Allegheny Home Rule Charter Info, December 1997-May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Allegheny Charter Technical Report, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Clippings, January-November 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
- Newspaper Clippings, January-April 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
- Home Rule Charter Correspondence, May 1997-August 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Home Rule Charter Public Hearing Testimony, August 1997-March 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
- Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)